Muhammad Zain Asghar

Lahore, Punjab, Pakistan



raziali420@gmail.com

+923334296607



linkedin.com/in/muhammad-zainasghar-015179136

Summary

I am a certified accounting & finance professional from the Institute of Chartered Accountants of Pakistan currently working as a senior associate reporting directly to an Audit Partner.

I have had the opportunity of being involved in various special natures:

- Statutory audits
- Reviews
- Risk advisory
- Tax advisory
- Corporate advisory
- Validation

This exposure to a wide spectrum of clients with a variety of work experiences has provided me with an in-depth view of the key business processes, risk management procedures, accounting and internal control systems, corporate governance and regulatory as well as accounting framework for a range of industries as follows:

- Automobile
- Chemical
- Construction
- Electric
- Engineering
- Feed
- Fish
- Flooring
- Food
- Healthcare
- Import/Export
- Information Technology
- Pets
- Plastic
- Shoe
- Solar
- Steel
- Tanning
- Others

Area of experience:

- Accounting standards (IAS/IFRS)
- Financial Statements Preparation
- Financial Analysis & Reports
- Audit & Assurance

- Advisory
- Corporate Dealings
- Taxation

Experience

MAH Audit, Assurance & Tax Associate

MAH, Chartered Accountants

Jun 2021 - Present (1 year 10 months)

Role and responsibilities comprise:

- Preparing annual & limited scope financial statements for statutory audit & requirements of regulatory authorities:
- Communicating audit progress & findings in status meetings; highlighting unresolved issues; reviewing working papers; preparing final audit reports;
- Co-coordinating with legal, actuarial, valuers, & IT experts;
- Planning audits by understanding organization objectives, structure, policies, processes, internal controls, & external regulations; identifying risk areas; preparing audit scope & objectives; preparing audit programs;
- Assessing regulatory compliance & controls by executing audit programs; examining & analyzing records, reports, operating practices, and documentation;
- Assessing risks & internal controls by identifying areas of non-compliance; evaluating manual & automated financial processes & identifying weaknesses;
- Conducting business & audit risk assessment through client meetings via research & analysis;
- Evaluating internal controls, identifying control deficiencies, & making appropriate recommendations to the management;
- Preparation of analytical review for the year;
- Completion & review of the fieldwork;
- Discussion & finalization of issues; &
- Preparation & filing of:
- Income tax returns & challans (including advance tax).
- Monthly withholding tax returns/statements U/s 165 of Income Tax Ordinance, 2001.
- Sales tax returns.
- Tax compliance & filing work.
- · Strategizing with clients to minimize tax liability.
- Maintaining clients' confidentiality.
- Advising on salary taxation & tax efficient salary structures as per law.
- Interpreting & analyzing legislative changes.
- Incorporating companies with SECP & registration of partnership firms & sole proprietors & advisory regarding SECP.
- Income tax, EOBI & sales tax registration.

Corporate & Tax Associate

RSM Avais Hyder Liaquat Nauman Chartered Accountants

Dec 2020 - Apr 2021 (5 months)

Role and responsibilities comprised:

- Preparation & filing of the following according to the clients' relevant portals:
- Corporate income tax returns & challans (including advance tax).
- Monthly withholding tax returns/statements U/s 165 of Income Tax Ordinance, 2001
- Sales tax returns.
- Individual tax returns.
- Tax compliance and filing work for the taxpayers
- Deferred tax workings
- Strategizing with clients to minimize tax liability.
- Maintaining clients' confidentiality relating to their tax matters.
- Performing pre- and post-submission checks of VAT/ST returns.
- Providing VAT/ST advice to the business and interacting with different stakeholders.
- · Advising on salary taxation to employees and tax-efficient salary structures as per law.
- Issuance of Refunds from tax authorities.
- Arranging exemption certificates for resident & non-resident companies.
- Interpreting and analyzing legislative changes.
- Tax litigations & exemption cases follow-up.
- Dealing with notices of FBR & Appeal sections.
- Appeal filing.
- Incorporating companies with SECP & registration of partnership firms & sole proprietors.
- Income tax, EOBI & sales tax registration.
- Advised clients' according to their requirements regarding SECP.
- · Sectors Served:
- Oil & Gas
- Energy & Power Generation
- Engineering & Construction
- Information Technology
- Tanning Industry
- Health Care
- Development & Education
- Automobile Assembler/Dealer

Account Executive

Highbrow International

Oct 2019 - Nov 2020 (1 year 2 months)

Role and responsibilities comprised:

- Monthly review of accounts receivable and payable.
- Feeding over-pending data into the system to bring it up to date.
- Bank reconciliations & resolution of related issues.
- Preparation of financial performance reports w.r.t the pending data.

Audit Internee

99 Industries (PVT) Ltd

Jul 2019 - Sep 2019 (3 months)

- 1) Learned the aspects of control systems of industry & applications of controls in the work environment.
- 2) Reviewed the work of staff with controls.
- 3) Checked the implementation of general accounting principles as per IFRS.

Education

■ The Institute of Chartered Accountants of Pakistan

Chartered Accountancy 2017 - Present

Skills

Bookkeeping • Consolidation • Appeals • Compliance Management • Corporate Tax • Accounts Receivable (AR) • Accounts Payable • Tax Accounting • Financial Accounting • Auditing